{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Sidney Fox attributed this event to \"proteinoid microspheres.\" Svante Arrhenius was a subscriber to the \"panspermia\" theory, which holds that this process occurred due to the arrival of alien microbes. The Miller-Urey experiment concerned the formation of amino acids necessary for this process. For 10 points, identify this starting point of evolution on Earth.",
      "answer": "origin of life"
    },
    {
      "question": "The discoverer of this body wanted to call it Georgium Sidus, but was overruled by colleagues. The discoverer of this planet also first observed its moons Titania and Oberon. Another planet was discovered when John Couch Adams noticed irregularities in this planet's motion. For 10 points, name this planet discovered by William Herschel, the first new planet since antiquity.",
      "answer": "Uranus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s doctoral thesis studied the degree of brain myelinization in white rats. With Harvey Karr, this man conditioned rats to run into walls when food was moved from its previous location in a maze. This engineer of the Kerplunk! experiment supposedly invented the coffee break in an ad campaign. With Rosalie Rayner, he conditioned a nine-month old boy to fear furry objects in the “Little Albert” experiment. For ten points, name this American psychologist who founded the school of behaviorism.",
      "answer": "John Broadus Watson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1995, this organization’s LEAR created the nine atoms of anti-hydrogen, the first true antimatter. This group’s AWAKE plasma experiment uses equipment and space once dedicated to the “Neutrinos to Gran Sasso” project. In 2012, scientists with this organization announced experimental data suggesting the finding of the Higgs boson. For ten points, name this research organization, based near Geneva, that operates the Large Hadron Collier.",
      "answer": [
        "CERN or the European Organization for Nuclear Research",
        "the Organisation europ´een pour la Recherche Nucl´eaire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The North and South basins of this body of water are separated by what used to be the Lisan Peninsula. The Mesha Stele, or Moabite Stone, was discovered along its banks. A pillar overlooking this body of water is known as “Lot’s wife.” The Qumran caves along its shore were home to a sect of Essenes whose writings were rediscovered beginning in 1946. A set of “scrolls” were discovered near, for ten points, what salty body of water bordered by Jordan, the West Bank, and Israel?",
      "answer": "Dead Sea"
    },
    {
      "question": "In his work as an astrologer, this scientist gained notoriety after successfully predicting a Turkish incursion and an extremely cold winter. In this scientist’s Mysterium Cosmographicum, he proposed that the six known planets are organized in a system defined by Platonic solids. This assistant to Tycho Brahe [ty-ko bra-hee] noted that Mars sweeps out equal areas in equal times and travels in an elliptical orbit. For ten points, name this German astronomer who discovered the three laws of planetary motion.",
      "answer": "Johannes Kepler"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The first known scientist to propose this theory was Aristarchus of Samos, who based his hypothesis on estimating the sizes of the objects involved. This theory, which argued in opposition to the Ptolemaic [toh-le-may-ik] model, was promoted in Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems, a book that led to Galileo’s house arrest. For ten points, name this astronomical theory proposed by Copernicus as a replacement for geocentrism.",
      "answer": [
        "heliocentrism",
        "word forms",
        "descriptions of “the Sun is at the center of the Solar System and/or Universe",
        "”",
        "descriptions of “the Earth or planets, etc. orbits the Sun"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The inventor of this technique worked at the Cetus Corporation and was lambasted in a 2007 New York Times article for believing in astrology, denying AIDS, and calling climate change a hoax. This technique greatly improved following the discovery of an enzyme capable of staying stable at high temperatures known as Taq [”tak”]. This technique allowed for the development of DNA testing by criminal investigators. Kary Mullis invented, for ten points, what laboratory technique that can amplify a sample of DNA?",
      "answer": "polymerase chain reaction or PCR"
    },
    {
      "question": "Shuck Yee invented a machine to mass produce these things, which Seiichi Kito claims were inspired by the Omikuji tradition. A tea garden was said to have been the venue where the first of these were served in the 1890’s; that example was allegedly baked in San Francisco. Sesame seed oil is generally used to make, for ten points, what foodstuff that was notably not invented in China and contains a supposed prophecy on a paper slip?",
      "answer": "fortune cookie"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these devices was co-developed by the developer of the Heimlich maneuver and the original voice actor of Tigger. At Wayne State University, one of these devices was used in a surgery on Henry Opitek after he was found to be suffering shortness of breath. The first of these devices was invented by Vladimir Demikhov while experimenting on dogs. One of these devices designed by Robert Jarvik has tubing made of polyurethane and contains pneumatically-fuelled ventricles. For ten points, name this medical device, a manmade version of a critical organ.",
      "answer": "artificial hearts"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1887 experiment involving a block of sandstone floating in mercury failed to find the fringe shift expected by a “wind” generated by this substance. This substance is supposed to be dragged by the Earth moving through it, a process not detected by the Michelson-Morley experiment. The theory of relativity was able to explain the non-existence of, for ten points, what hypothetical substance through which light moves, according to a theory that was finally debunked in the early 20th century?",
      "answer": "luminiferous aether"
    },
    {
      "question": "A museum dedicated to this man is located in Hamden, Connecticut, on the grounds of a gun factory that he built there. Prior to becoming an inventor, this man had planned to attend law school after graduating from Yale, where a non-traditional student admissions program is named for him. After this man popularized interchangeable parts, the federal government contracted him to help manufacture arms. For ten points, name this American inventor of the cotton gin.",
      "answer": "Eli Whitney"
    },
    {
      "question": "This person’s 1766 appearance before Parliament helped convince the British government to repeal the Stamp Act. This man’s son was the last colonial governor of New Jersey. Harry Meanwell and Silence Dogood are just two of this author’s many aliases. This man improved the catheter, invented the glass harmonica, and founded the University of Pennsylvania. For ten points, name this “First American,” famous for his kite experiment and Poor Richard’s Almanac.",
      "answer": "Benjamin Franklin 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 3"
    },
    {
      "question": "The pro-democratic Cylon and Ninon helped expel this man from Crotone [[croh- TOH-nay]] after he helped defeat Sybaris. This man studied the relationship between string length and musical note pitch, devising the Harmony of the Spheres theory for the planets. This man banned eating fava beans, and one of his followers was killed for revealing the existence of irrational numbers. For ten points, name this Greek polymath whose namesake theory says a squared plus b squared equals c squared.",
      "answer": "Pythagoras of Samos"
    },
    {
      "question": "The name for this object was suggested by an eleven-year old, and other suggested names for it were Zeus and Percival. When this heavenly body was discovered by Clyde Tombaugh in 1930, it disproved Percival Lowell's Planet X theory. Neil deGrasse Tyson said that allowing this object to be a planet would be an \"insult\" to the other planets. For ten points, name this trans-Neptunian dwarf planet in the Kuiper [[KY-per]] Belt that was once called the \"Ninth Planet\".",
      "answer": "Pluto 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
    },
    {
      "question": "Isaac Newton theorized this substance was composed of corpuscles in his book Opticks. That particle theory of polarization of this substance was mainstream until Robert Hooke developed the \"pulse theory\" and compared this form of radiation to waves of water in his book Micrographia. Years later, Max Planck [[PLAHNK]] described this type of radiation as a wave that can gain or lose finite amounts of energy, known as \"quanta.\" For ten points, name this type of electromagnetic radiation that can be seen by human eyes.",
      "answer": "Visible Light 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's work on animal respiration utilized his friend and human guinea pig Armand Séguin [[seh-GWEEN]]. This scientist disproved the historically popular phlogiston [[FLOH-jis-tahn]] theory by showing that nothing new is produced by combustion. This man formulated the law of conservation of mass and named oxygen and hydrogen before being executed during the French Revolution. For ten points, name this French scientist who is considered the father of modern chemistry.",
      "answer": "Antoine Lavoisier"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these particles was posited by Sheldon Glashow to solve the Cabibo theory. The discoverer of these particles named them after a nonsense word in Finnegans Wake and developed the SU(3) system for classifying them, which he called the Eightfold Way. For 10 points, name these building blocks of subatomic particles, discovered by Murray Gell-Mann.",
        "answer": "quarks"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1979 experiment in Hamburg confirmed the existence of what particles, which carry the color force between quarks?",
        "answer": "gluons"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first calculated the angular radius of a rainbow using Snell's Law. This man, who believed that the pineal gland joined the body to the soul, first used two axes to display four quadrants, creating his namesake coordinate plane. For 10 points, name this mathematician and philosopher who stated \"cogito ergo sum\" or \"I think therefore I am.\"",
        "answer": "Rene Descartes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Descartes also discovered what technique for determing the possible numbers of a function's roots by examining the pattern of positive and negative terms?",
        "answer": "Descartes's rule of signs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Robert Hooke first observed the shadows cast by these objects. In 1612, these objects supposedly vanished from Galileo’s sight; in reality, their edge’s plane aligned with Earth. Gaps between these objects were discovered by and named for Giovanni Cassini. For ten points, name these fine grains of ice and rock that form several disks around the sixth planet from the Sun.",
        "answer": "rings of Saturn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Dutch scientist, who also invented the pendulum clock and discovered Saturn’s moon Titan, was the first to identify the “ears” surrounding Saturn as a ring. A NASA probe named for this man was brought to Titan by the Cassini orbiter in 2004.",
        "answer": "Christaan Huygens"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory utilizes a coordinate system on a four-dimensional manifold named for Hermann Minkowski. Motivation for this theory was provided by the Michelson-Morley and Trouton-Noble experiments suggesting the non-existence of luminiferous aether. This theory introduced the notion of mass-energy equivalence and assumes nothing can travel faster than the speed of light. For ten points, name this theory proposed by Albert Einstein in 1905, ten years before a similar “General” theory.",
        "answer": "special relativity"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The group of spacetime isometries used in special relativity is named for this French mathematician, who also names a topological conjecture that was proved by Perelman in 2003.",
        "answer": [
          "Henri Poincare",
          "Poincare conjecture",
          "theorem"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This philosopher identified the lowest-level, indivisible units of substance as “monads.” This thinker formulated a principle of “pre-established harmony” in his Discourse on Metaphysics, and he codified the “principle of sufficient reason” in a 1710 work whose title coined the term “theodicy.” The inspiration for Pangloss in Voltaire’s Candide was, for ten points, what German thinker who concluded that ours is the best of all possible worlds?",
        "answer": "Gottfried Wilhelm von Leibniz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Leibniz’s non-philosophical work included the development of this mathematical field contemporaneously with, and independently of, Isaac Newton.",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Venetia Burney coined the name of this location, which is home to mountains named for Tenzing Norgay and Edmund Hillary. The discovery of this location used a blink comparator used by Clyde Tombaugh. In a book titled for How I Killed this object and Why it Had it Coming, Michael Brown recounted how this location was reclassified after his discovery of Eris, a trans-Neptunian body. The first Kuiper [kye-per] belt object to be discovered was, for ten points, what dwarf planet that was once classified as the ninth planet from the Sun?",
        "answer": "Pluto"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Astronomer Mike Brown also discovered this dwarf planet, the third largest-known trans- Neptunian object after Pluto and Eris. It takes its name from a Hawaiian goddess.",
        "answer": "Haumea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist was succeeded by Sir Aaron Klug on a project that determined the structure of the polio virus at Birkbeck College. This scientist split research on another project with Maurice Wilkins, and with graduate student Raymond Gosling, this scientist used X-ray diffraction to create her famous Photo 51. For ten points, name this English scientist whose work on determining the structure of DNA was co-opted by Watson and Crick.",
        "answer": "Rosalind Elsie Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Using Gosling and Franklin’s work, both Franklin and the Watson-Crick team determined that the A and B forms of DNA have this structure.",
        "answer": "right-handed double helix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "French chemist Hippolyte Mège-Mouriès made the first instance of this food after experimenting with a fatty acid discovered by Michel Eugene Chevreul and named for pearls. Henry Bradley patented a process to make this food from cottonseed oil rather than beef fat. Historically, New York and New Jersey forced this food to be colored pink instead of yellow as part of a color ban. For ten points, name this food whose creation stemmed from a challenge set forth by Napoleon III to furnish the military with a butter substitute.",
        "answer": [
          "Margarine",
          "Oleo",
          "Oleomargarine,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chevreul was one of only two living scientists whose names were included among the 72 inscribed on this structure when its construction was completed in 1889.",
        "answer": "Eiffel Tower 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the hopes of helping a certain species avoid the plague, scientists performed this procedure on a black-footed ferret named Willa. Early steps towards understanding this process included the discovery of embryotic induction by German scientist Hans Spemann [[SHPEH-mahn]]. The Roslin Institute in Scotland managed to perform this process on a mammal for the first time with a sheep named Dolly. For ten points, name this biological process of producing organisms with matching DNA.",
        "answer": [
          "Cloning",
          "Clones"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Cloning has been performed on many animals since the 1980s, including this type of monkey, which was the subject of controversial social isolation experiments by Harry Harlow.",
        "answer": "Rhesus macaque or Rhesus Monkey 2021-22 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-11-03 Round 10"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Computer Scientists",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Brit who cracked the German Enigma machine but was ostracized for his homosexuality.",
          "answer": "Alan Turing"
        },
        {
          "question": "“father of the computer” who created the Analytical Engine, an early mechanical computer.",
          "answer": "Charles Babbage"
        },
        {
          "question": "woman whose work on the aforementioned Analytical Engine credits her with creating the first computer algorithm.",
          "answer": "Ada Lovelace"
        },
        {
          "question": "admiral for the US Navy who invented the first compiler and coined the term computer bug.",
          "answer": "Grace Hopper"
        },
        {
          "question": "British knight who is credited with inventing the World Wide Web.",
          "answer": "Sir Tim Berners-Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "co-founder of Google with Sergey Bryn and the namesake of Google’s rank algorithm.",
          "answer": "Larry Page"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dutch computer scientist whose namesake shortest-path algorithm simplified Dutch transportation systems.",
          "answer": "Edsgar Dijkstra"
        },
        {
          "question": "founder of information theory who studied cryptography for Bell Labs during World War II.",
          "answer": "Claude Shannon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "North American Expeditions",
      "prompt": "Name the…...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ocean the Jesup Expedition explored off the coast of British Columbia.",
          "answer": "Pacific Ocean"
        },
        {
          "question": "Expedition across the Louisiana Purchase also called the Corps of Discovery.",
          "answer": [
            "Lewis and Clark Expedition",
            "Corps of Discovery if answer before mentioned"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that ceded Pacific Northwest Claims to the US in the Adams-Onís Treaty.",
          "answer": [
            "Spain",
            "Spanish Empire"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President who ordered the Corps of Discovery expedition.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Highly predictable feature discovered by the 1870 Washburn-Langford-Doane Expedition in Wyoming.",
          "answer": "Old Faithful"
        },
        {
          "question": "Russian Peninsula explored by Vitus Bering before coming to North America.",
          "answer": "Kamchatka"
        },
        {
          "question": "Geologist whose expedition was the first US government-sponsored passage through the Grand Canyon.",
          "answer": "John Wesley Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rail magnate who headed Union Pacific and led the 1899 scientific expedition to Alaska.",
          "answer": "Edward H. Harriman 2020-21 B-Set History Bowl - 2021-02-03 Round 4 The Viking Age"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's treatise Mechanics advanced the notion that inertia is derived from the mass of every other body in the universe, now known as his \"principle.\" His History of Mechanics introduced to Einstein the idea of non-absolute space. This German (20 pts)",
        "philosopher of science who also discovered shock waves produced when the (10 pts)",
        "speed of sound is exceeded. For 10 points, identify this man who thus lends his name to a \"number\" denoting the proportion to the speed of sound."
      ],
      "answer": "Ernst Mach"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man published regular weather data in his Meteorological Observations. As he was\nless influential in his own time than Jakob Berzelius, it was Berzelius's endorsement which\nled to acceptance of his ideas. He was the first to state what is now called (20 pts) ",
        "Charles's Law\nand form a theory about red-green colorblindness, as well as the law of (10 pts) ",
        "partial pressures.\nFor 10 points, name this early nineteenth century British scientist who popularized the modern\nidea of atoms."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Dalton",
        "Dalton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1987, this agent was found in the preserved body of Robert Rayford, who had died in St. Louis in 1969. In 1983, this agent was independently discovered by Robert Gallo and (20 pts)",
        "Luc Montagnier, who were investigating a disease then known as GRIDS. Gaetan Dugas is sometimes called the (10 pts)",
        "\"Patient Zero\" of this virus in the United States. For 10 points, name this retrovirus discovered in 1983 to be the cause of AIDS."
      ],
      "answer": "HIV"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One scientist from this country gives his name to the excretory system of spiders and is considered the father of microscopic anatomy. One scientist from this country discovered “animal (20 pts)",
        "electricity;” another scientist from this country built on that discovery to invent the first electrochemical battery. (10 pts)",
        "Alessandro Volta worked in, for ten points, what country where Galileo studied physics by dropping balls off the Leaning Tower of Pisa?"
      ],
      "answer": "Italy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One scientist with this last name proposed the fission theory of the moon. Another scientist with this last name described the inheritance of acquired characteristics in the 1794 work Zoonomia. Another scientist with this last name wrote (20 pts)",
        "The Descent of Man and names a group of finch species he saw on the Galapagos Islands during his voyage on the (10 pts)",
        "HMS Beagle. For ten points, give the surname of the author of On the Origin of Species, who showed natural selection was a means of evolution."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Darwin",
        "George Darwin, Erasmus Darwin",
        "Charles Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1894, a scientist working at this man’s namesake institute discovered the Yersinia pestis bacteria that spreads bubonic plague. This scientist’s research into silkworm diseases helped save his country’s agriculture industry. This man also saved a (20 pts)",
        "boy, Joseph Meister, who had suffered serious dog bites, in 1885. This scientist built on the work of Edward (10 pts)",
        "Jenner to develop vaccines against anthrax and rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process heats food to kill harmful microorganisms in foods like milk."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After Maria Mitchell discovered one of these objects in 1847, Christian VIII of Denmark presented her with a medal. Eight of these objects were discovered by Caroline Herschel, whose brother William discovered the (20 pts)",
        "planet Uranus; one of Caroline’s discoveries was found to be periodic in 1819 by Johann Encke, who now names it. One of these objects appears on the (10 pts)",
        "Bayeux Tapestry and famously appeared in the years of Mark Twain’s birth and death. For ten points, name these astronomical bodies, the most famous of which is named for Edmund Halley."
      ],
      "answer": "comets"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man asserted a reaction-diffusion theory of morphogenesis in his namesake patterns, which explain why nature has stripes, spots, and spirals. This man developed a sequential analysis technique in statistics that measures evidence using (20 pts)",
        "“bans.” The highest prize that the ACM offers is named for this man, whose namesake test determines if a machine is (10 pts)",
        "sufficiently intelligent. This man developed a bombe device to decrypt the Enigma machine. For ten points, name this British mathematician who modeled computation with his namesake machine."
      ],
      "answer": "Alan Turing"
    }
  ]
}